<p>During this past summer and my last semester at UMass I read a few good books:</p><dl><dt>Tall Trees and Wild Bees</dt><dd><a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7615752">Stewart Coffin</a> writes about growing up in Amherst.</dd><dt>The Last Man on the Moon</dt><dd>Astronaut Eugene Cernan's biography that he wrote with coauthor Don Davis.</dd><dt>Wise Blood</dt><dd>My suggestion for the Page to Screen book club, a novel by Flannery O'Connor.</dd><dt>As I Lay Dying</dt><dd>1930 novel by William Faulkner, set in Mississippi.</dd><dt><a href="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/leo-tolstoy/hadji-murad/aylmer-maude">Hadji Murád</a></dt><dd>Leo Tolstoy's story as translated by Aylmer Maude.</dd></dl><p>Also during the semester I wrote an SVG to stylize the initials of the recreational math club. It's supposed to look similar to Escher's <cite>Circle Limit</cite> series, and is based on the surface of a <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q11420123">mucube</a> with a repeating pattern. The thinly outlined quadrilaterals are distorted square faces.</p><figure><img height="400" loading="lazy" src="https://home.6t.lt/67f/o6-rmc-design.svg" alt="Circular graphic featuring the letters R M C and resembling an order-6 square tiling of the hyperbolic plane."/></figure><section class="projects art svg"><h3 class="fl"><span class="fl">Granjon Boxes</span></h3><p>I started working on a font which will recreate some of the typographical ornaments designed by <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q321678">Robert Granjon</a>. A few years ago, in an essay by <a href="https://elliotoffner.com/bio.html">Elliot Offner</a>, I was introduced to the following set of six pieces of moveable type which can serve as the building blocks for complex printed arabesques.</p><figure class="art"><img height="50" loading="lazy" src="https://home.6t.lt/690/six-piece-arabesque.png" alt="Six decorative characters printed to a binary bitmap."/></figure><p>Offner published <cite>The Granjon Arabesque</cite>, which is a book showcasing thirty arrangements pressed using these characters. The glyphs that I've added to the <cite>Granjon Boxes</cite> font so far are based on photos I took of the book's pages.</p><button class="fl"><samp>╺┑┏╸╺┑┏╸╺┑┏╸╺┑┏╸<br/>┨┝┫├┨┝┫├┨┝┫├┨┝┫├<br/>┖╴╶┘┖╴╶┘┖╴╶┘┖╴╶┘</samp></button><p>The arrangement of Unicode box-drawing characters above is my recreation of a design featured on page 105 of <cite><a href="https://www.tug.org/TUGboat/tb41-3/tb129reviews-vervliet.pdf">Granjon's flowers</a></cite> by Hendrik D. L. Vervliet. The characters were traced in Inkscape, creating an SVG file, which was converted to WOFF2 using FontForge. The 2025 version of <cite>Granjon Boxes</cite> contains the characters <q><code>┑┘┖┏╺╸╷╻╴╶╹╵┝┫┬┰┨├┻┷</code></q> and the space character U+20. The <a href="https://home.6t.lt/fonts">fonts directory</a> on this website will include the latest version licensed under the SIL Open Font License.</p><p>If you're reading this on my website, you should be able to click on the arrangements and reveal the typical box-drawing character designs by displaying them in the <cite><a href="https://www.kreativekorp.com/software/fonts/ksquare/">Kreative Square</a></cite> font.</p><button class="fl"><samp>┬┨├┰┬┨├┰┬┨├┰┬┨├┰<br/>┝┻┷┫┝┻┷┫┝┻┷┫┝┻┷┫</samp></button><p>These designs have been digitized before. The much more comprehensive font <cite><a href="https://www.juanjez.com/designing-a-revival-graveur/">Graveur</a></cite> by Juanjo López is based on the work of Robert Granjon and also includes some of the same decorative characters. Another book of arrangements, <cite>Kleines Spiel mit Ornamenten</cite> by Max Caflisch, was digitized and translated from German to French by Jacques André and published online: <cite><a href="https://jacques-andre.fr/faqtypo/orn/jeux.pdf">Petits jeux avec des ornements</a></cite>.</p></section><section class="featured"><h3><span class="fl">Found on home.6t.lt</span></h3><ul><li><a href="https://home.6t.lt/atom.xml">Atom feed for the blog</a> (or <a href="https://home.6t.lt/feed.json">JSON feed</a>)</li><li><a href="https://home.6t.lt/shortcuts/note/">Text box for note-taking</a></li><li><a href="https://home.6t.lt/?s=%23mirror_polygon_66c">Mirror polygon drawing tool</a></li><li><a href="https://home.6t.lt/?s=%23percent_encode_677">Percent-encoding guide</a></li><li><a href="https://home.6t.lt/?s=:is(p,dl,ol,ul):has(a%5Bhref%5E=%22http%22%5D)">All external links from the blog</a></li><li><a href="https://home.6t.lt/shortcuts/strings/">String manipulation tool</a></li></ul></section><section class="art encodings"><h3>Window Painting</h3><figure id="window_68f"><img height="105" loading="lazy" src="https://home.6t.lt/68a/sel-window.webp" alt="Photo of a geometric floral window painting."/></figure></section>